<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-10T17:19:56+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Security Policy</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Security_Policy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Security Policy"/><published>2024-09-20T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-20T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Security_Policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Security_Policy/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>A set of rules and practices that specify how a system or organization provides security services to protect its assets.</p> </blockquote> <p>Security policy defines the measures that are in place to <u>ensure the confidentiality, integrity, and availability</u> of data, networks, and system.</p> <h1 id="things-covered">Things covered</h1> <ul> <li><strong>Who can access what</strong>: explain who is allowed to use certain computers, programs, and information</li> <li><strong>How to keep data safe</strong>: provide steps for keeping data safe from being stolen or lost</li> <li><strong>What to do if something goes wrong</strong>: give instructions on how to handle problems like computer hacks, data breaches, or other security issues</li> <li><strong>Using the internet and emails safely</strong>: provide guidelines for using the internet and emails in a way that doesn’t put the organization at risk</li> <li><strong>Making sure software is up to date</strong>: explain why it’s important to regularly update software and how to do it</li> <li><strong>Training employees</strong>: include instructions for teaching employees about security risks and how to protect the organization</li> <li><strong>Physical security</strong>: might cover things like locking doors, keeping servers in safe places, and making sure only authorized people can enter certain areas</li> </ul> <h1 id="aspects-of-security">Aspects of Security</h1> <blockquote> <p>The security architecture provides a systematic approach to address the dynamic and evolving nature of security challenges in information systems.</p> </blockquote> <p>It offers a framework for organizations to build and maintain a secure environment for their <u>data, systems, and networks</u> by focusing on attacks, mechanisms, and services.</p> <h2 id="security-attack">Security Attack</h2> <p>These attacks can take <strong>various forms</strong>, unauthorized access, disclosure, modification, or destruction of data, systems, or networks.<br/> The goal is to protect against such actions and maintain the confidentiality, integrity, and availability of information (CIA Traids).</p> <h2 id="security-mechanism">Security Mechanism</h2> <p>Methods designed to detect, prevent, or recover from security attacks. They act as security barriers to safeguard an organization’s assets. They operate independently or in conjunction.</p> <h3 id="common-security-mechanisms">Common security mechanisms</h3> <ul> <li>Cryptography</li> <li>Message digests and digital signatures</li> <li>Digital certificates</li> <li>Public Key Infrastructure (PKI): A framework that manages digital keys and certificates, facilitating secure communication. &amp;nbsp Different entieties excange information using digital certification</li> </ul> <h2 id="security-service">Security Service</h2> <p>It is functionalities offered by security mechanisms to enhance the security of a system. And it represent the specific functionalities offered by security mechanisms. It can include authentication, access control, data confidentiality, data integrity, and non-repudiation.</p> <h3 id="authentication">Authentication</h3> <blockquote> <p>Used to assure the identity of the sender or creator of the data. It is a process of verifying the identity of a user, device, or system, to ensure that it is not and imposter or malicious actor.</p> </blockquote> <p>=&gt; Assure that the communicating entity is the one that it claims to be</p> <h4 id="two-specific-authentication-services">Two specific authentication services</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Peer Entity Authentication</strong>: Used to authenticate the identity of other entities with which the system is communicating</li> <li><strong>Data Origin Authentication</strong>: Used to authenticate the origin of a message or data, to ensure that it was sent by the entity that it claims to be form</li> </ul> <p>Both of these services are important for ensuring the authenticity and integrity of communication, in order to prevent unauthorized access, tampering, or impersonation. It ensures that the data or communication is from the intended source and not an imposter or an attacker.</p> <p><strong>Process</strong>: Identification -&gt; Authentication -&gt; Authorization -&gt; Auditing -&gt; Accountability -&gt; IAAA</p> <h3 id="access-control">Access Control</h3> <blockquote> <p>It used to prevent misuse of resources and ensure that only authorized users have access to the available rewources.</p> </blockquote> <p>=&gt; Prevent unauthorized use of a resource</p> <h4 id="examples">Examples</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Discretionary Access Control (DAC)</strong>: allows the owner or administrator of a resource to decide who is allowed to access it</li> <li><strong>Role-based Access Control (RBAC)</strong>: allows access based on the role of the user within the organization. ex) AWS account</li> <li><strong>Mandatory Access Control (MAC)</strong>: the access is granted based on a set of predefined rules</li> <li><strong>Attribute-based Access Control (ABAC)</strong>: the access is granted based on the attributes of the requestor, the resource, and the context in which the access request is made</li> </ul> <h3 id="data-confidentiality">Data Confidentiality</h3> <blockquote> <p>Responsible for ensuring that the data is <u>kept extremely safe from third-party intruders.</u></p> </blockquote> <p>=&gt; Protect data from unauthorized disclosure</p> <h4 id="types-of-data-confidentiality">Types of data confidentiality</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Protecting data in transit</strong>: to protect data that is being transmitted between two parties, over a network or through the internet. Can include both passive and active protection measures, encryption.</li> <li><strong>Protecting data at rest</strong>: to protect data that is <u>stored on a device or system</u>, on a HD or in a DB. Can include access controls, encryption, and backups to prevent unauthorized access or data loss.</li> <li> <p><strong>Protecting traffic flow from analysis</strong>: to protect the characteristics of the traffic flow, the source and destination, frequency, length and other characteristics of the traffic on a communication facility. Can include measures such as traffic padding and traffic encryption.</p> </li> <li>Data Confidentiality services are important for maintaining the privacy and security of sensitive information, and they can take many forms to protect data in transit, at rest and traffic flow from analysis.</li> </ul> <h3 id="data-integrity">Data Integrity</h3> <blockquote> <p>Ensure that the transmitted information received by the receiver is <strong>well-authenticated</strong> and there is <u>no tampering with the information received.</u></p> </blockquote> <p>=&gt; Assure data received are exactly as sent by authorized entity</p> <p>Helps to ensure that the data received is the same as the data that was sent and that it has not been <strong>modified</strong>, <strong>deleted</strong>, or <strong>tampered</strong> <u>with in any way.</u></p> <ul> <li>Data Integrity services are important for <u>maintaning the authenticity and accuracy of transmitted information</u>, and they can take many forms to protect a stream of messages, individual messages, or selected fields within a message.</li> </ul> <h3 id="nonrepudiation">Nonrepudiation</h3> <p>Used to prevent either sender or receiver of a transmitted message from denying that the message was sent or received.</p> <p>=&gt; Protect against denial of one entity involved in communications of having participated in communications</p> <ul> <li><strong>Message is sent</strong>: the receiver can prove that the alleged sender in fact sent the message</li> <li><strong>Message is received</strong>: the sender can prove that the alleged receiver in fact received the message</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Security/Security_Services-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Security/Security_Services-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Security/Security_Services-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Security/Security_Services.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <ul> <li><em>CS458-Introduction to Information Security</em>. (2024). Sajad Meisami, Ph.D. Illinois Institute of Technology.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info_Security"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Information Security]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Security Basic - Easiest penetration &amp;amp; Defense of Computer Systems</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-EasiestPenetration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Security Basic - Easiest penetration &amp;amp; Defense of Computer Systems"/><published>2024-09-19T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-19T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-EasiestPenetration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-EasiestPenetration/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="principle-of-easiest-penetration">Principle of Easiest Penetration</h1> <ul> <li>Security principle:<br/> &amp;nbsp - A system is only as secure as its weakest link<br/> &amp;nbsp - An attacker will often target the easiest poin of encry in a system rather than the most obvious one</li> </ul> <p>Emphasizes the importance of identifying and addressing potential vulnerabilities in a system. As well as testing and regularly reviewing the security controls that are in place.</p> <h2 id="devsecops-processing">DevSecOps processing</h2> <ol> <li>Initialization Requirement</li> <li>Design<br/> &amp;nbsp - Threat modeling: Secure Design, Archetiecture</li> <li>Build Implementation<br/> &amp;nbsp - Secure code practice</li> <li>Testing<br/> &amp;nbsp - Static Analysis, Dynamic Analysis, Interactive Analysis, SCA</li> <li>Deployment Release</li> <li>Maintenance</li> </ol> <p>Authentication \(\in\) Threat modeling</p> <h1 id="principle-of-adequate-protection">Principle of Adequate Protection</h1> <p>It highlights the need for balancing the cost of security measures with the potential impact of security incidents.<br/> Also, advises organizations not to overspend on security measures to protect a system that would only cause limited damage if compromise. This principle considers both technical and economic factors in implementing the most effective security measures to protect the assets.</p> <ul> <li>A proper security risk assessment</li> <li>To weigh the costs and the risks</li> <li>Make sure the right protection measures are in place, balance; Not too much or too little</li> </ul> <h1 id="balancing-information-security-and-access">Balancing information security and access</h1> <p>This requires a balance between ==protection and availability==, known as the security vs. accessibility trade-off.<br/> Includes balancing the need to protect sensitive information with the need to allow employees, customers, and other stakeholders access to that information.</p> <ul> <li>The goal is to find a balance that ensures the ==confidentiality, integrity, and availability of information== while enabling the organization to function effectively.</li> </ul> <h1 id="cryptography">Cryptography</h1> <blockquote> <p>Cyprtography is the practice of protecting data by convering it into an unreadable format (encryption) that can only be accessed by someone who has the proper decryption key.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="common-uses">Common uses</h2> <ul> <li>Protecting data by making it unreadable through the use of encryption algorithms</li> <li>Authenticating users with digital signatures<br/> &amp;nbsp - use a combination of encryption and hashing to prove the identity of the sender</li> <li>Authenticating transactions with cryptographic protocols, SSL/TLS<br/> &amp;nbsp - provide secure communication between web browsers and servers</li> <li>Ensuring the integrity of stored data by using cryptographic techniques<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) Message Authentication Codes (MAC)</li> <li>Aid customers’ privacy by having their personal information automatically become unreadable after a certain length of time</li> </ul> <h1 id="software-controls">Software controls</h1> <blockquote> <p>Security measure that are used to protect computer systems and networks from unauthorized access and other types of threats.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="examples">Examples</h2> <ul> <li>Passwords and other forms of access control<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) biometric authentication</li> <li>Operating systems that include built-in security features<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) user accounts and permissions, be used to separate users’ actions from each other on a system</li> <li>Virus scanners watch for some kinds of malware</li> <li>Develpment controls enforce quality measures on the original source code</li> <li>Personal firewalls</li> </ul> <h1 id="hardware-controls">Hardware controls</h1> <blockquote> <p>Security measure that use separate hardware devices to protect computer systems and networks</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="examples-1">Examples</h2> <ul> <li>Biometric readers<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) fingerprint readers</li> <li>Smart tokens<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) small and portable decices that generate one-time passcodes</li> <li>Firewalls</li> <li>Intrusion detection systems</li> </ul> <h1 id="physical-controls">Physical controls</h1> <blockquote> <p>Security measure that are designed to protect the hardware itself and prvent physical access to the console, storage media, and other critical components of a computer system or network.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="examples-2">Examples</h2> <ul> <li>Locks</li> <li>Security guards</li> <li>Off-site backups: To protect against the possibility of fire, flood, or other types of natural disasters</li> <li>Location-based controls<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) Do not put data center on a fault line in California</li> </ul> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <ul> <li><em>CS458-Introduction to Information Security</em>. (2024). Sajad Meisami, Ph.D. Illinois Institute of Technology.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info_Security"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Information Security]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Security Basic 2</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Security Basic 2"/><published>2024-09-17T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-17T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic2/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="computer-security-concepts">Computer Security Concepts</h1> <ul> <li>Asset</li> <li>Vulnerability</li> <li>Threat</li> <li>Attack</li> <li>Countermeasure or control</li> </ul> <h2 id="asset">Asset</h2> <blockquote> <p>Things might want to protect</p> </blockquote> <ol> <li>Hardware: Includeing computer systems and other data processing, data storage.</li> <li>Software: Including the operating system, system utilities, and applications.</li> <li>Data: Including files and databases, as well as security-related data.<br/> &amp;nbsp&amp;nbsp ex) password files</li> <li>Communication facilities and networks: Local and wide area network communication links, bridges, routers, and so on.</li> </ol> <h2 id="vulnerabilities">Vulnerabilities</h2> <blockquote> <p>Weaknesses or gaps in the security system that could be exploited to cause loss or harm.</p> </blockquote> <p>Weakness can be occur through flaws`, features or user error, and attackers will look to exploit any of them, often combining one or more, to achieve their end goal.</p> <p><strong>Flaws</strong></p> <ul> <li> <p>It is an unitended funcitonality. This may either be a result of poor design or through mistakes made during implementation. Flaws may go undetected for a significant period of time. The majority of common attacks we see today exploit these types of vulnerabilities.</p> </li> <li> <p>Vulnerabilities are actively pursued and exploited by the full range of attackers consequently, a market has grown in software flaws, with “zero-day” vulnerabilities fetching hundreds of thousands of dollars.</p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="examples">Examples</h3> <ul> <li>A file server that doesn’t authenticate its users</li> <li>Bad passwords</li> <li>Buggy software</li> <li>Untrained employees</li> <li>Lack of encryption</li> </ul> <h3 id="categories">Categories</h3> <ul> <li>Corrupted (Loss of integrity): The system can be <strong>corrupted</strong>, so it does the wrong thing or gives wrong answers.<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) Stored data values may differ from what they should be because they have been improperly modified.</li> <li>Leaky (Loss of confidentiality): The system can be <strong>leaky</strong>.<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) Someone who should not have access to some or all of the information available through the network obtains such access.</li> <li>Unavailable or very slow (Loss of availability): The system can become <strong>unavailable</strong> or very slow.<br/> &amp;nbsp -&gt; using the system or network becomes impossible or impractical.</li> </ul> <h2 id="threats">Threats</h2> <blockquote> <p>Threats are <strong>potentials</strong> for vulnerabilities to turn into attacks on systems. Threats are potential dangers or harmful events that could exploit vulnerabilities in a system or organization, leading to negative impacts.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="attacks">Attacks</h2> <blockquote> <p>An action which explits a vulnerability to execute a threat.</p> </blockquote> <p>Attacks (threats carried out) lead to compromises or security breaches.</p> <p>Can be classified as Passive and Active.<br/> *Passive: Attempt to learn or make use of information from the system that does not affect system resources.<br/> *Active: Attempt to alter system resources or affect their operation.</p> <p>Also be classified based on the source/origin of the attacks, Inside attack and Outside attack.<br/> *Inside attack: Initiated by entity <strong>with authorized access</strong> to system.<br/> *Outside attack: Initiated by <strong>unauthorized user</strong> of the system.</p> <h3 id="example">Example</h3> <ul> <li>Telling the file server you are a different user in an attempt to read or modifiy their files are ways to exploiting a vulnerability to damage assets.</li> <li>Bad passwords: using password crackers</li> <li>Buggy software: launching an SQL injection attack</li> <li>Untrained employees: tricking them to share their credentials</li> <li>Lack of encryption: eavesdropping on communications</li> </ul> <h2 id="risk">Risk</h2> <blockquote> <p>The potential for loss, damage or destruction of an asset as a result of a threat exploiting a vulnerability.</p> </blockquote> <p>It is the likelihood that a threat will exploit a vulnerability to cause damage to an asset.<br/> Combination of the potential impact and the probability of a threat occurring.</p> <h3 id="example-1">Example</h3> <ul> <li>Financial losses</li> <li>Loss of privacy</li> <li>Damage to your reputation</li> <li>Legal implications</li> <li>Even loss of life</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Security/Security_concepts-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Security/Security_concepts-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Security/Security_concepts-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Security/Security_concepts.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <ul> <li><em>CS458-Introduction to Information Security</em>. (2024). Sajad Meisami, Ph.D. Illinois Institute of Technology.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info_Security"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Information Security]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Security Basic 1</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Security Basic 1"/><published>2024-09-15T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-15T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic/"><![CDATA[<p>There are few keywords in the security.</p> <ul> <li> <p><em>Confidentiality</em>:<br/> Information and data need to be kept <strong>confidential</strong> in order to protect sensitive information, personal information, trade secrets, and financial data.</p> </li> <li> <p><em>Integrity</em>:<br/> It helps to ensure the integrity of data and systems <u>by protecting against unauthorized modification or destruction</u>. It is important that maintaining the accuracy and reliability of information and systems.</p> </li> <li> <p><em>Availability</em>:</p> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info_Security"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Information Security]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ML Project Log 1</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/ML-Log-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ML Project Log 1"/><published>2024-06-15T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-15T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/ML%20Log%201</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/ML-Log-1/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="what-i-did">What I did</h1> <p>Fix the error that not plotting Agglomerative Clustering plot when the user choose ‘Agglomerative Cluster’.</p> <p>Edit the flow of the website.<br/> -&gt; In the first page, there are two button to choose the options, ‘Clustering’ and ‘Classification’. After choose, upload the file.</p> <h1 id="processing">Processing</h1> <p>Almost done clustering function after fix error after upload the file.</p> <h1 id="comment">Comment</h1> <p>Not used to Flask, so need to learn more about Flask.</p> <h1 id="what-i-need-to-do">What I need to do</h1> <p>Need to fix error after upload the file. Need to make functions for classification.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="DevLog"/><category term="project"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Processing and issue of ML Project and what I learn during this project]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IaaS vs PaaS vs SaaS</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Cloud_computing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IaaS vs PaaS vs SaaS"/><published>2024-05-08T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-08T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Cloud_computing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Cloud_computing/"><![CDATA[<p>IaaS, PaaS, and SaaS are the three most popular types of cloud service offerings. They are sometimes referred to as cloud service models or cloud computing service models.</p> <h1 id="infrastructure-as-a-service">Infrastructure as a service</h1> <p>Also known as IaaS. It is on-demand access to cloud-hosted physical and virtual servers, storage, and networking - the backend IT infrastructure for running applications and workloads in the cloud. The difference is that the cloud service provider hosts, manages, and maintains the hardware and computing resources in its own data centers. IaaS customers use the hardware via an internet connection and pay for that use on a subscription or pay-as-you-go basis. Customers can provision, configure and operate the servers and infrastructure resources via a graphical dashboard, or programmatically through APIs.</p> <p>IaaS is like a Lego factory.</p> <h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2> <ol> <li><strong>Flexibility</strong> : Compared to traditional IT, IaaS gives customers more <strong>flexibility</strong> to build out computing resources as needed and to scale them up or down in response to spikes or slow-downs in traffic.</li> <li><strong>Reduction of customer costs and overhead</strong> : It lets customers avoid the up-front expense and overhead of purchasing and maintaining its own on-premises data center.</li> <li><strong>Scalability</strong> : It eliminates the constant tradeoff between the waste of purchasing excess on-premises capacity to accommodate spikes, versus the poor performance or outages that can result from not having enough capacity for unanticipated traffic bursts or growth.</li> <li><strong>Higher availability</strong> : The company can effortlessly set up backup servers and even deploy them in different locations to guarantee continued operation in case of local power failures or physical disasters.</li> <li><strong>Lower latency, and improved performance</strong> : Because IaaS providers typically operate data centers in multiple geographies, IaaS customers can locate apps and services closer to users to minimize latency and maximize performance.</li> <li><strong>Improved responsiveness</strong> : Customers can quickly set up resources, try out new ideas rapidly, and easily introduce them to a larger audience.</li> <li><strong>Comprehensive security</strong> : With strong security measures in place at the office, data centers, and encryption, organizations can often benefit from enhanced security and protection similar to what they would have if they managed the cloud infrastructure themselves.</li> <li><strong>Faster access to best-of-breed technology</strong> : Cloud providers compete by offering cutting-edge technologies to their users. Customers using IaaS can benefit from these technologies much sooner and at a lower cost compared to implementing them in their own physical locations.</li> </ol> <h2 id="usage">Usage</h2> <ul> <li>Disaster recovery</li> <li>Ecommerce</li> <li>IoT, event processing, AI</li> <li>Startups</li> <li>Software development</li> </ul> <h1 id="platform-as-a-service">Platform as a service</h1> <p>As known as PaaS. It provides a cloud-based platform for developing, running, and managing applications. The cloud services provider hosts manages and maintains all the hardware and software included in the platform, servers, OS software, storage, networking, databases, middleware, runtimes, frameworks, and development tools. Also provide related services for security, OS and software upgrades, and backups.</p> <p>Users can access PaaS through GUI. Development or DevOps teams can collaborate on all their work across the entire application lifecycle, coding, integration, testing, delivery, deployment, and feedback.</p> <p>PaaS is like a Lego brick. PaaS developer provides the Lego bricks to the software developers and the software developers make their own Lego model using the bricks. They do not need to make their own Lego bricks for their service; they just choose the bricks and pay for them.</p> <h2 id="benefits-1">Benefits</h2> <ol> <li><strong>Efficiency</strong> : Allows customers to build, test, deploy run, update, and scale applications more quickly and cost-effectively than they might if they had to build out and manage their own on-premises platform.</li> <li><strong>Faster time to market</strong> : Development teams are able to spin-up development, testing, and production environments in minutes, rather than weeks or months using PaaS.</li> <li><strong>Low- to no-risk testing and adoption of new technologies</strong> : Typically, a PaaS platform has an application that includes access to a wide range of up-to-date resources above and below the stack. This enables enterprises to operate new OS without significant investment in systems, languages, and other tools. Users can test the infrastructure required to test or run their system, language, and other tools.</li> <li><strong>Simplified collaboration</strong> : As a cloud-based service, PaaS provides a shared software development environment, giving development and operations teams access to all the tools they need, from anywhere with an Internet Connection.</li> <li><strong>A more scalable approach</strong> : With PaaS, organizations can purchase extra capacity for building, testing, staging, and running applications whenever they need it.</li> <li><strong>Less to manage</strong> : PaaS offloads infrastructure management, patches, updates, and other administrative tasks to the cloud service provider.</li> </ol> <h2 id="usage-1">Usage</h2> <ul> <li>API development and management</li> <li>IoT</li> <li>Agile development and DevOps</li> <li>Cloud-native development and hybrid cloud strategy</li> </ul> <h1 id="software-as-a-service">Software as a service</h1> <p>As known as SaaS. It is cloud-hosted, ready-to-use application software. Users pay a monthly or annual fee to use a complete application from within a web browser, desktop client, or mobile app. The application and all of the infrastructure required to deliver it-servers, storage, networking, middleware, application software, data storage-are hosted and managed by the SaaS vendor. Simply, the user does not need to download the software to use.</p> <p>The vendor manages all upgrades and patches to the software. As part of the Service Level Agreements (SLAs), vendors ensure availability, performance, and security levels. Customers can add more users and data storage on demand by paying extra.</p> <p>Email, social media, and cloud file storage solutions are examples of SaaS applications. The chatGPT is SaaS product.</p> <p>SaaS is like already made the Lego model.</p> <h2 id="benefits-2">Benefits</h2> <ol> <li><strong>Convenience</strong> : SaaS offloads all infrastructure and application management to the SaaS vendor. All the user has to do is create an account, pay the fee, and start using the application. The vendor handles everything else, from maintaining the server hardware and software to managing user access and security, storing and managing data, implementing upgrades and patches, and more.</li> <li><strong>Minimal risk</strong> : There is a free trial period or low monthly fees provided by most SaaS providers. Let customers try the software to get used to it or see if it will meet their needs.</li> <li><strong>Anytime/anywhere productivity</strong> : If there is an internet connection, the customers can use SaaS products anytime and anywhere. Adding users is as simple as registering and paying for new seats - customers can purchase more data storage for a nominal charge.</li> </ol> <p>Some SaaS vendors allow the user to customize their product from provided a companion PaaS solution.</p> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <p>What are iaas, paas and SAAS?. IBM. (2024, March 8). https://www.ibm.com/topics/iaas-paas-saas</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Cloud_Computing"/><category term="WIS"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of IaaS, PaaS, and SaaS]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DBSCAN</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/DBSCAN/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DBSCAN"/><published>2024-03-29T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/DBSCAN</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/DBSCAN/"><![CDATA[<div class="jupyter-notebook" style="position: relative; width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;"> <div class="jupyter-notebook-iframe-container"> <iframe src="/assets/jupyter/sample_DBSCAN.ipynb.html" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; border-style: none;" width="100%" height="100%" onload="this.parentElement.style.paddingBottom = (this.contentWindow.document.documentElement.scrollHeight + 10) + 'px'"></iframe> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI"/><category term="Data_Mining"/><category term="WIS"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of DBSCAN Function]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial Neural Network</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2023/ANN/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial Neural Network"/><published>2023-10-17T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-17T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2023/ANN</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2023/ANN/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1> <blockquote> <p>A branch of machine learning models that are built using principles of neuronal organization discovered by connectionism in the biological neural networks constituting animal brains.</p> </blockquote> <p>An Artificial Neural Network (ANN) teaches computers to process data inspired by the human brain. It is a type of deep learning that uses nodes or neurons interconnected in a hierarchical structure similar to the human brain. Hidden layers are needed if the data must be separated using a <strong>non-linear</strong> boundary. Generalize the single neuron perceptron to a more complex architecture of nodes capable of learning nonlinear decision boundaries.</p> <h2 id="what-is-the-difference-between-ann-and-perceptron">What is the difference between ANN and Perceptron</h2> <p>The major difference is the inclusion of hidden layers. Perceptron can create only <mark>one</mark> hyperplane.</p> <h1 id="structure-of-ann">Structure of ANN</h1> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ANN/layer-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ANN/layer-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ANN/layer-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/ANN/layer.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="three-kinds-of-neural-networks">Three kinds of neural networks</h2> <h3 id="1-feed-forward-neural-networks-ffnn">1. Feed Forward Neural Networks (FFNN)</h3> <p>General neural networks for classification, regression, etc.</p> <h3 id="2-convolutional-neural-networks">2. Convolutional neural networks</h3> <p>Excel at image recognition.</p> <h3 id="3-recurrent-neural-networks">3. Recurrent neural networks</h3> <p>Excel at language tasks.</p> <h2 id="hidden-layer">Hidden Layer</h2> <p>It can be viewed as learning potential representations or features that are useful to differentiate classes. Also, it dramatically improves their ability to represent arbitrarily complex decision boundaries. Hidden nodes learn potential representation features useful for class boundaries. The first hidden layer captures simpler features since it receives the predictors as input. Subsequent hidden layers hone specific patterns of the data to extract features.</p> <h1 id="activation-function">Activation Function</h1> <p>It provides non-linearity to an ANN and allows it to create non-linear class boundaries.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ANN/activation_function-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ANN/activation_function-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ANN/activation_function-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/ANN/activation_function.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <a href="https://www.v7labs.com/blog/neural-networks-activation-functions">V7 labs</a> </div> <h2 id="how-to-choose">How to choose?</h2> <p>Match the activation function at the output layer <u>based on the type of prediction problem</u>.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>- Regression : Linear activation function.

	$$\sigma(z) = z$$

- Binary classification : Sigmoid / Logistic activation function.
	$$\begin{align} \sigma(z) &amp;= \frac{1}{1 + e^{-x}} \\ \sigma^{'}(z) &amp;= \sigma(z) \cdot (1 - \sigma(z)) \end{align}$$

- Multiclass classification : Softmax activation function.

	$$\sigma(z_i) = \frac{e^{z_i}}{\sum_{j = 1}^{k}{e^{z_j}}}, \;\; for \;\; i = 1, \cdots, k \;\; and \;\; z = (z_1, \cdots, z_k) \in R$$
	
- Multilabel classification : sigmoid activation function.

	$$\begin{align} \sigma(z) &amp;= \frac{1}{1 + e^{-z}} \\ \sigma^{'} &amp;= \sigma(z) \cdot (1 - \sigma(z)) \end{align}$$
	
- Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) : ReLU activation function.

	$$\begin{align} \sigma(z) &amp;= max(0, z) \\
	\sigma^{'}(z) &amp;= \begin{cases} 1, \;\; if \;\; z &gt; 0 \\ 0, \;\; if \;\; z ≤ 0 \end{cases} \end{align}$$

- Recurrent Neural Network : Tanh and/or Sigmoid activation function.

	$$\begin{align} \sigma(z) &amp;= \frac{e^{z} - e^{-z}}{e^{z} + e^{-z}} \\ 
	\sigma^{'}(z) &amp;= 1 - tanh^{2}(z) \end{align}$$
</code></pre></div></div> <p>For the hidden layers, start with <strong>ReLU</strong> activation function and move to others if results are sub-optimal.</p> <h2 id="example">Example</h2> <p>Use the sigmoid at the hidden layers and the output layer. \(\sigma(z) = \frac{1}{1 + e^{-z}}\)</p> <p>Loss : \(\frac{1}{2}\sum_{i = 1}^{n}{(\hat{y_i} - y_i)^2}\)</p> <ul> <li>Initialize \(\vec{w}\) <ul> <li> \[\vec{w} = N(0, \sigma^2)\] <ul> <li>if \(\sigma^2\) too small : the output will <strong>converge</strong> to 0</li> <li>if \(\sigma^2\) too large : the output will <strong>diverge</strong></li> <li>Xavier initialization : \(\sigma^2 = \frac{2}{n_in + n_out}\)</li> <li>He initialization : \(\sigma^2 = \frac{2}{n_in}\)</li> </ul> </li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>The network input to the neuron : \(z = w^Tx = \sum_{i = 1}^{n}{w_i x_i} = w_1x_1 + \cdots + w_nx_n\)</p> <p>The output from the neuron : \(\sigma(w^Tx) = \sigma(z)\)</p> <h1 id="feed-forward-neural-network">Feed-Forward Neural Network</h1> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ANN/FFNN%20example-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ANN/FFNN%20example-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ANN/FFNN%20example-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/ANN/FFNN%20example.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>X = [1, 4, 5], y = [0.1, 0.05]</p> <p>Input for \(h_1\) : \(z_{h1} = (x_1w_1 + x_2w_3 + x_3w_5) = (1\times0.1) + (4\times0.3) + (5\times0.5) = 3.8\)</p> <p>Output for \(h_1\) : \(\sigma(z_{h1}) = \sigma(3.8) = \frac{1}{1 + e^{-3.8}} = 0.98\)</p> <p>Input for \(h_2\) : \(z_{h2} = (x_1w_2 + x_2w_4 + x_3w_6) = (1\times0.2) + (4\times0.4) + (5\times0.6) = 4.8\)</p> <p>Output for \(h_2\) : \(\sigma(z_{h2}) = \sigma(4.8) = \frac{1}{1 + e^{-4.8}} = 0.99\)</p> <p>Input for \(o_1\) : \(z_{o1} = (\sigma(z_{h1})\times w_7 + \sigma(z_{h2})\times w_9) = (0.98\times0.7) + (0.99\times0.9) = 1.58\)</p> <p>Output for \(o_1\) : \(\sigma(z_{o1}) = \sigma(1.58) = \frac{1}{1 + e^{-1.58}} = 0.83\)</p> <p>Input for \(o_2\) : \(z_{o2} = (\sigma(z_{h1})\times w_8 + \sigma(z_{h2})\times w_{10}) = (0.98\times0.8) + (0.99\times0.1) = 0.88\)</p> <p>Output for \(o_2\) : \(\sigma(z_{o2}) = \sigma(0.88) = \frac{1}{1 + e^{-0.88}} = 0.71\)</p> <p>Loss: \(\frac{1}{2}[(\sigma(z_{o1}) - y_1)^2 + (\sigma(z_{o2}) - y_2)^2] = \frac{1}{2}[(0.83 - 0.1)^2 + (0.71 - 0.05)^2] = 0.48\)</p> <h1 id="backpropagation">Backpropagation</h1> <p>To reduce the loss / error use the Backpropagation method. The chain rule is used for the backpropagation. \(\begin{align} \frac{\partial E}{\partial w_7} &amp;= \frac{\partial E}{\partial \sigma(z_{o1})} \cdot \frac{\partial \sigma(z_{o1})}{\partial z_{o1}} \cdot \frac{\partial z_{o1}}{\partial w_7} \\ &amp;= [(\sigma(z_{o1}) - y_1)]\cdot [\sigma(z_{o1})(1 - \sigma(z_{o1}))]\cdot [\sigma(z_{h1})] \\ &amp;= [(0.83 - 0.1)]\cdot [(0.83 - (1 - 0.83)]\cdot [0.98] \\ &amp;= 0.10 \end{align}\) \(\frac{\partial E}{\partial w_1} = \frac{\partial E}{\partial \sigma(z_{h1})} \cdot \frac{\partial \sigma(z_{h1})}{\partial z_{h1}} \cdot \frac{\partial z_{h1}}{\partial w_1}\)</p> <p><strong>Result</strong> A gradient vector of weights is used for updating the weights to get to the minimum gradient (Jacobian matrix). \(\nabla E = [\frac{\partial E}{\partial w_1}, \frac{\partial E}{\partial w_2}, \frac{\partial E}{\partial w_3}, \frac{\partial E}{\partial w_4}, \cdots, \frac{\partial E}{\partial w_n}]^T = [0.61, 0.87, 0.21, \cdots, 0.99]^T\) Update the weight with this gradient vector: $w_{new} = w_{old} - \eta \nabla E$</p> <h2 id="gradient-descent">Gradient descent</h2> <p>Use gradient descent algorithm for error (or cost) function minimization and to minimize the error function with respect to the weights. This algorithm is used in the training dataset to modify weights during each epoch to minimize the cost or error.</p> <h3 id="types">Types</h3> <ul> <li>Batch gradient descent : Calculate the error for each observation and perform the update $w$ by calculating the mean error at the end of the training data.</li> <li>Stochastic gradient descent : Calculate the error for each observation and update $w$.</li> <li>Mini-batch gradient descent - Preferred method <ul> <li>Divide the data into small batches, calculate the error for each placed observation, and perform the update $w$ by calculating the mean error at the end of the batch.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <ul> <li>CS 422, Data Mining, prof. Vijay K. Gurbani, Fall 2023, Illinois Institute of Technology</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI"/><category term="Data_Mining"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Artificial Neural Network]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial Neural Network - Perceptron</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2023/Perceptron/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial Neural Network - Perceptron"/><published>2023-10-07T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-07T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2023/Perceptron</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2023/Perceptron/"><![CDATA[<p>The perceptron was investigated in 1957 by Frank Rosenblatt at Cornell. It was the first learning algorithm based on the concept of a neural network.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Perceptron/neuron_anatomy-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Perceptron/neuron_anatomy-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Perceptron/neuron_anatomy-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Perceptron/neuron_anatomy.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The perceptron was guaranteed to find the linear boundary between two classes if there is a boundary. The perceptron is a simple <strong>one-cell</strong>, most simplest, neural network. It is characterized as a <strong>feed-forward</strong> neural network that solves linearly separable problems. -&gt; If the data is linearly separable, the perceptron will find the hyperplane that separates it.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Perceptron/linear_seperable-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Perceptron/linear_seperable-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Perceptron/linear_seperable-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Perceptron/linear_seperable.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>More complex neural networks can solve data mining or learning tasks more effectively by gathering several perceptrons. They work together to solve the task.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Perceptron/diagram-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Perceptron/diagram-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Perceptron/diagram-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Perceptron/diagram.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>We can train a model to derive a hyperplane that will separate the classes, but there are two conditions. i) Dealing with a binary classification problem such as \(y_i \in \{-1, +1\}\) ii) Data is linearly separable.</p> <p>Training is all about adjusting the weight parameter, <em>w</em>, until the response predicted by the perceptron becomes consistent with the true response.</p> <p>However, even for binary classes, the perceptron cannot recognize the XOR function. To solve this, we need the multiple perceptron model. This is a general neural network.</p> <h2 id="example">Example</h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Perceptron/perceptron_example-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Perceptron/perceptron_example-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Perceptron/perceptron_example-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Perceptron/perceptron_example.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>In this case, 0.3 is weight, and 0.4 is bias. We can write it as a formula, \(\hat{y} = \begin{cases} 1: 0.3x_1 + 0.3x_2 + 0.3x_3 + 0.4 \ge 0 \\ -1: 0.3x_1 + 0.3x_2 + 0.3x_3 + 0.4 &lt; 0 \end{cases}\) This could be rewritten as \(\begin{align} \hat{y} &amp;= sign((\sum_{i=i}^{n}{w_i x_i}) + b) \\ &amp;= sign (\sum_{i = 0}^{n} {w_i \times x_i}) \\ &amp;= sign(w_i \cdot x_i) \end{align}\)</p> <p>Note: \(sign(x) := \begin{cases} -1 \;\;\; if \;\; x &lt; 0, \\ 0 \;\;\;\;\;\; if \;\; x = 0, \\ 1 \;\;\;\;\;\; if \;\; x &gt; 0 \end{cases}\)</p> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <ul> <li>CS 422, Data Mining, prof. Vijay K. Gurbani, Fall 2023, Illinois Institute of Technology</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI"/><category term="Data_Mining"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Perceptron]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is GPT?</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2023/GPT/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is GPT?"/><published>2023-08-30T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-30T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2023/GPT</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2023/GPT/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>GPT is Generative pre-trained transformers. It is a type of large language model and a prominent framework for generative artificial intelligence.</p> </blockquote> <p>There are two ways that AI develops a language model. The first is to use a person’s language as a statistic. The second is to use a neural network. Using the neural network is better performance. Google also uses this method on its search engine to predict what the user is about to search for.</p> <p>GPT is a conditional probability prediction tool underlying natural language processing. The difference between human beings and GPT is a vast amount of learning. When human beings write an article or essay, we write and fix and repeat it until we think it is done or perfect. However, GPT is not doing the same process as we do. When a user types the keywords, GPT gathers every data related to the keywords and makes the text article what the user asked.</p> <p>GPT models are based on transformer architecture. The concept of transformer architecture was first introduced in the report ‘Attention is all you need’ published by Google Brain in 2017. After that, the competition began to build a supermodel capable of handling various language tasks, Google’s BERT, MS’s Turing NLG, and OpenAI’s GPT3. Then which generation of GPT is used for ChatGPT is GPT 3.5. Because of this vast amount of train, developments in GPT language models have had a significant impact on natural language processing and other applications that rely on text data.</p> <h1 id="history-of-gpt">History of GPT</h1> <p>OpenAI introduced the first GPT in the world in 2018. The amount of the first GPT was trained with 117 million parameters. A year later, in 2019, the second GPT was released to the public by OpenAI. At this time, it was trained with 1.5 billion which is 10 times larger. The second GPT could write a page of the book in 10 seconds. In 2020, there was an upgraded version, GPT 3. It was trained with 175 billion parameters. What we can do with the third GPT is various language-related problem-solving, random writing, simple rule calculation, translation, and simple coding according to a given sentence.</p> <h2 id="before-gpt">Before GPT</h2> <p>Before transformer architecture technology was introduced, ‘generative pretraining’ was a long-established concept in machine learning applications. The most effective neural models for Natural Language Processing (NLP) typically utilize supervised learning using extensive volumes of data that have been labeled manually.</p> <h1 id="limitations">Limitations</h1> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Pre-training</strong> : It should be pre-trained. This is the major difference between human beings and GPT. When we have a conversation with others, we remember what we talked about previously, such as an hour or a week ago, but GPT does not. GPT does not have an ongoing long-term memory that learns from each interaction.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Limited input size</strong> : A user cannot provide a lot of text as input for the output. GPT3 has a prompt limit of about 2,048 tokens. It means that, for example, we cannot ask for translation over what it can handle.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Slow inference time</strong> : GPT3 has a slow inference time because the model takes a long time to generate results.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Lack of explainability</strong> : GPT3 is prone to the same problems that many neural networks face. Lack of ability to explain and interpret why certain inputs result in certain outputs. It does not understand the nuance contained in the sentence or words, such as anger, happy, or delight.</p> </li> </ol> <h1 id="risks">Risks</h1> <ol> <li><strong>Mimicry</strong> : NLP models like GPT3 are continuously improving in accuracy, blurring the line between machine-generated content and human-written text, leading to challenges in distinguishing between them. This could potentially give rise to concerns related to copyright infringement and plagiarism.</li> <li><strong>Accuracy</strong> : Even though GPT3 excels at mimicking the structure of text produced by humans, it faces difficulties in maintaining factual precision across various use cases.</li> <li><strong>Bias</strong> : Language models carry a susceptibility to biases inherent in machine learning. These models are trained on internet text, they have the potential to internalize and reflect the biases prevalent in human online interactions. For instance, a pair of researchers at the Middlebury Institute of International Studies at Monterey discovered that GPT2 is proficient at producing extremist content, such as dialogues resembling those of conspiracy theorists and white supremacists. This situation opens the door to the automation and amplification of hate speech, often unintentionally. To address this concern, ChatGPT, built upon a version of GPT3, strives to mitigate such risks through more extensive training and incorporation of user input. There was this issue previously with the chatbot from MS.</li> </ol> <h1 id="problem">Problem</h1> <p>Ethics issues always come up when the latest technologies related to artificial intelligence are introduced every time, such as generating fake news, deep fake, and other misleading forms of content.</p> <p>We should establish related organizations and make related regulations globally before the technology develops further.</p> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <ul> <li> <p>Network, A. (2021, February 19). <em>GPT 모델의 발전 과정 그리고 한계</em>. Medium. <a href="https://medium.com/ai-networkkr/gpt-%EB%AA%A8%EB%8D%B8%EC%9D%98-%EB%B0%9C%EC%A0%84-%EA%B3%BC%EC%A0%95-%EA%B7%B8%EB%A6%AC%EA%B3%A0-%ED%95%9C%EA%B3%84-81cea353200c">Medium </a></p> </li> <li> <p>Wikimedia Foundation. (2023, August 13). <em>Generative pre-trained transformer</em>. Wikipedia. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generative_pre-trained_transformer#:~:text=The%20first%20GPT%20was%20introduced,generate%20novel%20human%2Dlike%20content.">Wikipedia </a></p> </li> <li> <p>Lutkevich, B., &amp; Schmelzer, R. (2023, August 17). <em>What is GPT-3? everything you need to know - techtarget</em>. Enterprise AI. <a href="https://www.techtarget.com/searchenterpriseai/definition/GPT-3">techtarget</a></p> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI"/><category term="WIS"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of GPT]]></summary></entry></feed>