<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-28T00:36:55+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Naive Bayes Classifier</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Naive-Bayes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Naive Bayes Classifier"/><published>2024-12-20T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-20T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Naive-Bayes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Naive-Bayes/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>Naive Bayes classifier is a family of linear <strong>Probabilistic classifier</strong>.<br/> -&gt; Assumes the features are conditionally independent given the target.</p> </blockquote> <p>This classifier is one of the types of the simplest Bayesian network models.<br/> Also, it is widely utilized for its simplicity and efficiency in machine learning.<br/> As it is the family of “linear” probabilistic classifier, it is highly scalable, requiring a number of parameters linear in the number of varibales in a learning problem.<br/> Naive Bayes classifier is mostly used in the language model. It is fast and making prediction is easy with high dimension of data. The naive Bayes classifier is based on Bayes’ Theorem, \(P(A|B) = \frac{P(B|A)P(A)}{P(B)}\), where A and B are events and \(P(B) \neq 0\).<br/> For more information on Bayes’ Theorem, check <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayes%27_theorem">Wikipedia</a>.</p> <h2 id="assumption">Assumption</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Feature independence</strong>: The features of the data are conditionally independent of each other.</li> <li><strong>Continuous features are normally distributed</strong>: If a feature is continuous, then it is assumed to be normally distributed within each class.</li> <li><strong>Discrete features have multinomial distributions</strong>: If a feature is discrete, then it is assumed to have a multinomial distribution within each class.</li> <li><strong>Features are equally important</strong>: All features are assumed to contribute equally to the prediction of the class label.</li> <li><strong>No missing data</strong>: The data should not contain any missing data.</li> </ul> <h2 id="advantages">Advantages</h2> <ul> <li>Easy to implement and computationally efficient.</li> <li>Effective in cases with a large number of features.</li> <li>Performs well even with limited training data.</li> <li>Performs well in the presence of categorical features.</li> <li>For numerical features data is assumed to come from normal distributions.</li> </ul> <h2 id="disadvantages">Disadvantages</h2> <ul> <li>Assumes that features are independent, which may not always hold in real-world data.</li> <li>Can be influenced by irrelevant attributes.</li> <li>May assign zero probability to unseen events, leading to poor generalization.</li> </ul> <h2 id="applications">Applications</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Spam email filtering</strong></li> <li><strong>Text classification</strong>: used in sentiment analysis, document categorization, and topic classification.</li> <li><strong>Medical diagnosis</strong>: helps in predicting the likelihood of a disease based on symptoms.</li> <li><strong>Credit scoring</strong>: Evaluates the creditworthiness of individuals for loan approval.</li> <li><strong>Weather prediction</strong></li> </ul> <h1 id="referrence">Referrence</h1> <ul> <li>CS 481, Artificial Intelligence Language Understanding, prof. Jacek Dzikowski, Spring 2024, Illinois Tech</li> <li>Comment, et al. “Naive Bayes Classifiers.” GeeksforGeeks, 10 July 2024, www.geeksforgeeks.org/naive-bayes-classifiers/.</li> <li>“Naive Bayes Classifier.” Wikipedia, Wikimedia Foundation, 28 Nov. 2024, en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naive_Bayes_classifier.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI/ML"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understand the concept of the Naive Bayes Classifier]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">k-Means Clustering</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/kMeansClustering/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="k-Means Clustering"/><published>2024-12-17T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/kMeansClustering</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/kMeansClustering/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="what-is-k-means-clustering">What is K-means Clustering</h1> <p>The k-Means algorithm is one of the most popular iterative descent clustering methods and the unsupervised learning’ algorithm. K stands for clustering which assigns data points to one of the K clusters based on the distance from the cluster center. Start by randomly assigning the cluster center to the space. Each data point is then assigned to one of the clusters based on the distance from the cluster center. Assign each point to one of the clusters and assign a new cluster center. This process runs repeatedly until a good cluster is found. Should assign points to one of the groups assuming that the number of clusters is given in advance in the analysis.<br/> It aim for situations where all variables are quantitative types, and select Euclidean distance squared as a measure of dissimilarity.<br/> \(d(x*{i}, x*{i'}) = \sum\_{j=1}^{p} {(x*{ij} - x*{i'j})^2} = \|\|{x\*{i} - x\_{i'}}\|\|^2\)</p> <p>In some cases, K is not clearly defined, and we have to think about the optimal number of K. K means clustering performs best when data is well separated. When data points overlap, this clustering is not suitable. To get help defining the K, we can use the ‘Silhouette score’ or the ‘Elbow method’ The criterion is minimized by allocating N observations to K clusters in such a way that the average difference from the cluster mean defined by the points of theat cluster within each cluster is minimized.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Unsupervised Learning</strong>: Uses machine learning to analyze unlabeled datasets to discover patterns without human supervision.</li> </ul> <h1 id="goal-of-clustering">Goal of Clustering</h1> <p>The goal of clustering is to divide a population or set of data points into groups so that data points within each group are more similar to each other and differ from data points within other groups. Clusters are essentially grouping objects according to how similar and different they are from each other and discover underlying patterns or structures within the data.</p> <h1 id="algorithm">Algorithm</h1> <ol> <li>For a given cluster assignment \(C\), the total cluster variance, \(\min*{C, {m*{k}}_{1}^{K}} {\sum_{k=1}^{K} {N*{k}} \sum*{C(i)=k} {\|\|x\*i - m*k\|\|^2}}\), is minimized with respect to \({m_1, \cdots, m_K}\) yiedling the means of the currently assigned clusters, \(\bar{x_S} = \argmin*{m} {\sum\_{i \in S} {\|\|x_i - m\|\|^2}}\).</li> <li>Given a current set of means \({m*{1}, \cdots, m*{K}}\), \(\min\_{C, {m_{k}}_{1}^{K}} {\sum_{k=1}^{K} {N_{k}} \sum_ {\|\|x_i - m_k\|\|^2}}\) is minimized by assigning each observation to the closest cluster means.<br/> \(C(i) = \argmin\_1 {\|\|x_i - m_k\|\|^2}\)</li> <li>Steps 1 and 2 are iterated until the assignments do not change.</li> </ol> <p>Each of the first and second steps reduces the value of the criterion to ensure convergence. However, the results may indicate a suboptimal local minimum. In addition, start the algorithm with various random choices for the starting means, and we need to select the solution with the smallest value of the objective function.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/k-means-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/k-means-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/k-means-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/k-means.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI/ML"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understand the concept of the k-Means Clustering]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Machine Learning Final Preparation</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/ML-Final_Prep/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Machine Learning Final Preparation"/><published>2024-11-27T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-27T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/ML-Final_Prep</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/ML-Final_Prep/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-the-condition-number-of-a-matrix-and-why-is-it-important-in-machine-learning">What is the condition number of a matrix and why is it important in Machine Learning?</h2> <ul> <li>The state of regulation of a matrix can be shown from its conditional number. In this case, a measure of how sensitive the solution to a linear equation is to the data changes or changes to the matrix itself.</li> </ul> <p>Condition numbers are, thus, important to understand in machine learning because they make our models unstable and, even worse, very sensitive and bad, in cases of using a regression training algorithm for our linear models.</p> <p>This means that a small perturbation or error may cause significant changes in the output for the same inputs. This is especially alarming in machine learning, which develops models using noisy or incomplete data. Model predictions can be negatively impacted by high sensitivity and may yield unreliable results.</p> <p>The condition number is not only significant for solution precision, but it is also paramount for the generalization of machine learning algorithms. Dress a matrix in a condition number that means that it is well conditioned, and you can have a much smoother landscape with a better optimization convergence during training and have models that generalize effectively to unseen data. On the other hand, under-conditioned models are likely to overfit the training data, which is a characteristic of lower generalization ability.</p> <h3 id="citation">Citation</h3> <ul> <li>Guggenheimer, H., Edelman, A., \&amp; Johnson, C. R. (1995). A Simple Estimate of the Condition Number of a Linear System. College Mathematics Journal. https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/epdf/10.1080/07468342.1995.11973657?needAccess=true</li> </ul> <h2 id="what-are-lasso-and-ridge-regularization-when-do-you-need-to-use-regularization-would-you-use-lasso-or-ridge-in-a-high-dimensional-problem-which-is-generally-more-accurate-why">What are LASSO and Ridge regularization? When do you need to use regularization? Would you use LASSO or Ridge in a high-dimensional problem? Which is generally more accurate? Why?</h2> <p>LASSO: A regression analysis method that enhances the prediction accuracy and interpretability of the resulting statistical model by performing both variable selection and regularization. Lasso penalizes based on the absolute value of the coefficients. It not only shrinks the coefficient but also some can be set to exactly zero, making it a variable selection technique.</p> <p>Ridge regularization: Adds a penalty equivalent to the square of the magnitude of coefficients. In this case, use an L2 norm of the coefficients, which shrinks all coefficients towards zero, but does not eliminate them. Additionally, Rdge performs better when the multicollinearity among the predictors is present.</p> <p>Using regularization is useful for high-dimensional datasets since it curbs excessive fitting of those datasets.</p> <p>I would use Lasso. It is also common practice to use Lasso in some cases due to its variable selection ability. It can shrink the model incrementally and eventually force some coefficients to be exactly zero. This could make the model simpler and more interpretable, possibly enhancing its performance in the presence of new data. However, Ridge, most of the time, incorporates all predictors, which might not be suitable in a situation when one is trying to build a prediction from the most crucial features.</p> <p>In essence, Ridge estimates tend to be better when there is high multicollinearity while all the features of the data are of interest because it yields more stable estimates in this case. To handle this concern, Ridge reduces the size of the coefficients and retains all the features thereby increasing the robustness of the analysis and the results.</p> <h3 id="citation-1">Citation</h3> <p>-Ranstam, J., Cook, J.A. (2018). LASSO regression. British Journal of Surgery, 105.</p> <h2 id="under-what-conditions-are-k-fold-cross-validation-and-bootstrapping-a-poor-choice-for-model-selection-what-are-some-alternatives-in-these-cases">Under what conditions are k-fold cross validation and bootstrapping a poor choice for model selection? What are some alternatives in these cases?</h2> <ul> <li> <h3 id="k-fold-cross-validation">k-fold cross-validation:</h3> </li> </ul> <ol> <li> <p>High-dimensional settings where predictors are independent of class labels but the model is allowed to select predictors, cross-validation may give misleadingly optimistic results if feature selection is not properly handled within the cross-validation process.</p> <ul> <li>Alternatives: Lasso / Ridge Regularization, PCA</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p>When there is considerable variability in the error estimates. Error estimates obtained from CV can show significant variability depending on how the data is split. Relying solely on the mean performance may lead to overestimating the model’s reliability.</p> <ul> <li>Alternatives: Repeated cross-validation, Bootstrap</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p>If the model is not completely retrained for each fold, including any feature selection or preprocessing steps. This is a common blunder even in top-ranked journal papers.</p> <ul> <li>Alternatives: Nested cross-validation</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p>When working with large numbers of predictors, such as in genomics, improper cross-validation implementation can have dramatic consequences in terms of incorrect error estimation.</p> <ul> <li>Alternatives: Regularization, Feature Filtering, Nested CV, PCA</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <ul> <li> <h3 id="bootstrapping">Bootstrapping</h3> </li> </ul> <ol> <li> <p>Unsupervised learning, such as clustering, because cluster centers will tend to fill feature space densely and be close to all data points regardless of K.</p> <ul> <li>Alternatives: cross-validation, AIC/BIC, Silhouette score, or elbow</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p>Leave-One-Out (K = N) Bootstrap. When K = N, where every data point is included except one. It is low bias and high variance. The training sets are almost identical across iterations, leading to a highly variable estimate despite low bias. Also, it has a high computational cost. Running N iterations can become computationally expensive.</p> <ul> <li>Alternatives: k-fold cross-validation</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p>The bootstrap error estimate does not provide a good estimate in general.</p> <ul> <li>Alternatives: cross-validation, AIC/BIC, Ensemble evaluaion</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p>Problems with standard errors that may be invalid due to the influence of the model selection process and optimization criteria after model selection that may differ from the desired criteria on the training set.</p> <ul> <li>Alternatives: Cross-validation, AIC/BIC</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p>Problems with traditional methods, such as F-statistics, that adding or removing terms based on significance fails to account for multiple testing issues adequately.</p> <ul> <li>Alternatives: AIC/BIC, cross-validation, Regularization (Lasso and Ridge)</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <h2 id="citation-2">Citation</h2> <ul> <li>Trevor Hastie, Robert Tibshirani, and Jerome Friedman, 2009, The Elements of Statistical Learning: Data Mining, Inference, and Prediction (Second Edition), Ch 7 : Model Assessment and Selection</li> </ul> <h2 id="give-a-brief-descrption-of-dropout-why-is-it-used-so-widely-in-deep-learning">Give a brief descrption of dropout. Why is it used so widely in Deep Learning?</h2> <ul> <li>To address overfitting, Dropout randomly sets a subset of neurons to zero at the start of each training cycle. This procedure increases robustness by preventing complex co-adaptations and forcing the network to learn redundant representations. Dropout, by its nature, makes the network less sensitive to individual neurons. As a result, this model can generalize and perform better on new, untested data. A more generalized representation that can manage different inputs is achieved using dropout, allowing each model update to be viewed as a mini-semble of multiple neural network topologies. It is also shown to improve performance on a wide range of tasks and datasets. Finally, it helps the model perform better and train faster. During training, it allows models to learn more efficiently and reach their best performance quicker by temporarily turning off some neurons during training.</li> </ul> <h3 id="citation-3">Citation</h3> <ul> <li>Byrd, J., \&amp; Lipton, Z. C. (2018). What is the Effect of Importance Weighting in Deep Learning? International Conference on Machine Learning. https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/b661520bf0061b7d96ccf12016e351dd3a6ee780</li> </ul> <h2 id="why-are-convolutional-layers-used-widely-in-image-classification-and-segmentation">Why are convolutional layers used widely in image classification and segmentation?</h2> <ul> <li>There are several reasons. First, it is utilized for an explicit feature extraction, which is localized in a region of interest. Such features are derived from local areas of the image, which enables the identification of edges, textures, and other low-level patterns. Second, these local features help in enhancing the correlation as well as the intensity of pixels from areas that are closer as opposed to those that are farther away. It is important to mention that during the image classification process, cure areas are concentrated, which makes local features even more significant.</li> </ul> <p>Second, it is utilized for the purpose of architecture that is economical. For instance, architecture that has been designed with weight sharing in mind for a structure such as a neural network can apply the same filters or kernels all over the entire image, thus minimizing the number of parameters, as well as the number of computations required to be performed. Such relevant units in the feature maps process little portions at a time while interrelating and distinguishing a pattern.</p> <p>Third, it is utilized for the hierarchical feature processing. Convolutional networks build hierarchical representations, starting with simple features and progressing to more complex patterns. In the same way, the local features detect some parts, which in the next stage get combined for general feature detection. Moreover, deep representations are less affected than shallow representations by transformations like translations, scaling, and small rotation of the images.</p> <p>Fourth, it is used in the context of invariance. Convolutional layers give consistent regions as patterns that can be recognized. Such patterns can also be enhanced through data augmentation or more sophisticated architectures to be invariant to scaling or rotations.</p> <p>Fifth, it is used for efficient learning of features and structures of patterns as well as deeper networks. Convolutional networks make use of local receptive fields, weight sharing, and subsampling to hit efficiently, and with so many processes, the image across features. Earlier networks with no invariances had average higher misclassification rates of around 4.5\%, but these architecture limitations have largely been alleviated by complementary ones other architectures have strengthened.</p> <p>Lastly, emphasizes other methods as wavelet transforms. In some of the tasks, wavelet transforms are used in conjunction with CNNs in order to increase edge detection and capture discrete jumps in images, although CNNs are now robust enough to perform such tasks independently.</p> <h2 id="citation-4">Citation</h2> <ul> <li>Bishop, C. M. (2006). Chapter 5: Neural networks. In Pattern recognition and machine learning. Springer.</li> <li>Trevor Hastie, Robert Tibshirani, and Jerome Friedman (2009), Ch 11: Neural Networks, The Elements of Statistical Learning: Data Mining, Inference, and Prediction (Second Edition)</li> </ul> <h2 id="if-model-a-gives-a-rmse-of-032-and-model-b-gives-a-rmse-of-034-same-training-and-out-of-sample-validation-sets-what-are-some-factors-you-would-consider-in-determining-which-is-the-better-model-why-are-these-factors-relevant">If Model A gives a RMSE of 0.32 and Model B gives a RMSE of 0.34 (same training and out-of-sample validation sets), what are some factors you would consider in determining which is the better model? Why are these factors relevant?</h2> <ul> <li>There are several factors to consider in determining which model is the better. First, model Complexity and interpretability. If the model is too complicated, then the risk of overfitting increases. The complex model has good performance in the train data, but it might not perform well in the new data. Also, too complex a model is hard to interpret, and there are possible debugging difficulties. The simple model makes it easy to understand the result or the processing of the prediction.</li> </ul> <p>Second, robustness to overfitting. If the model is overfitting to the training data, it does not generalize well to the new data. In particular, if the training data is low or noisy, the model is likely to overfit. Especially with less training data or too much noise, there is the possibility to be overfitting.</p> <p>Lastly, training time and resource efficiency. A more complicated model takes more time to train, and the time required to train models can increase exponentially, especially when trained on a large dataset. Also, a complex model such as a deep learning model can require significant computational resources.</p> <h3 id="citation-5">Citation</h3> <ul> <li>Bishop, C. M. (2006). Chapter 3: Linear Models for Regression. In Pattern recognition and machine learning. Springer.</li> <li>Trevor Hastie, Robert Tibshirani, and Jerome Friedman (2009), Ch 7: Model Assessment and Selection, The Elements of Statistical Learning: Data Mining, Inference, and Prediction (Second Edition)</li> <li>Goodfellow, I., Bengio, Y., \&amp; Courville, A. (2016). Chapter 5: Machine learning basics. In Deep learning. MIT Press. Retrieved from http://www.deeplearningbook.org</li> </ul> <h2 id="you-are-given-some-binary-classification-training-data-with-two-features-x_1-x_2-both-x_1-and-x_2-are-0-1-valued-you-can-easily-calculate-px1y-y-and-px2y-y-and-py-y-for-y-0-1-but-what-else-do-you-need-to-check-in-order-to-satisfy-the-conditions-for-using-a-naive-bayes-classifier">You are given some binary classification training data with two features $X_1$, $X_2$. Both $X_1$ and $X_2$ are {0, 1}-valued. You can easily calculate $P(X1|Y= y)$ and $P(X2|Y= y)$ and $P(Y= y)$ for $y= 0, 1$, but what else do you need to check in order to satisfy the conditions for using a Naive Bayes classifier?</h2> <ul> <li> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>We need to check the conditional independence of features given the class, $P(X_1, X_2</td> <td>Y = y) = P(X_1</td> <td>Y = y) \cdot P(X_2</td> <td>Y = y)$ and sufficient data, enough data to accurately estimate the conditional probabilities.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </li> </ul> <h3 id="citation-6">Citation</h3> <ul> <li>Bishop, C. M. (2006). Chapter 4: Linear Models for Classification. In Pattern recognition and machine learning. Springer.</li> </ul> <h2 id="are-association-rules-as-found-by-the-a-priori-algorithm-transitive-eg-if-a-rightarrow-b-and-b-rightarrow-c-does-a-rightarrow-c">Are association rules as found by the a priori algorithm transitive? (e.g. if $A \Rightarrow B$ and $B \Rightarrow C$, does $A \Rightarrow C$?)</h2> <ul> <li>No. It does not guarantee that $ A \Rightarrow C$ will also be valid if $A \Rightarrow B$ and $B \Rightarrow C$ are valid association rules. Because the strength of the association rule is determined by its support and confidence, but because $A \Rightarrow B$ and $B \Rightarrow C$ hold with high support and confidence does not imply that $ A \Rightarrow C$ will also hold with high support and confidence. The Apriori algorithm generates rules based on empirical patterns found in the data. The relationship between A and C is not guaranteed by the relationship found in $A \Rightarrow B$ or $B \Rightarrow C$. The association rules, however, rely on data rather than logical reasoning which may lead to no establishment of transferability.</li> </ul> <h3 id="citation-7">Citation</h3> <ul> <li>Tan, P.-N., Steinbach, M., &amp; Kumar, V. (2021). Chapter 5: Association analysis: Basic concepts and algorithms. In Introduction to data mining (2nd ed.). Pearson.</li> <li>Trevor Hastie, Robert Tibshirani, and Jerome Friedman (2009), Ch 14: Unsupervised Learning, The Elements of Statistical Learning: Data Mining, Inference, and Prediction (Second Edition)</li> </ul> <h2 id="is-the-following-statement-true-or-false-performing-pca-before-utilizing-another-classification-or-regression-model-can-reduce-the-number-of-input-features-and-improve-performance-and-therefore-is-a-good-idea-if-true-provide-some-supporting-details-if-false-give-a-counterexample">Is the following statement true or false? “Performing PCA before utilizing another classification or regression model can reduce the number of input features and improve performance and therefore is a good idea.” If true, provide some supporting details. If false, give a counterexample.</h2> <ul> <li>False. PCA captures linear correlations, so it may fail to preserve important nonlinear relationships in the data. Applying PCA can remove informative features, reducing the performance of the classifier or regressor. Also, PCA does not consider the label. PCA is the unsupervised method that does not make use of any labels in the computation. Therefore, if the classification or regression model is the supervised model, such as logistic regression and decision trees, then performing PCA before utilizing another model may not improve performance.</li> </ul> <h3 id="citation-8">Citation</h3> <ul> <li>Trevor Hastie, Robert Tibshirani, and Jerome Friedman (2009), Ch 3: Linear Methods for Regression, The Elements of Statistical Learning: Data Mining, Inference, and Prediction (Second Edition)</li> </ul> <h2 id="is-the-following-statement-true-or-false-performing-k-means-and-then-adding-labels-of-the-resulting-clusters-to-your-set-of-features-can-enhance-your-feature-set-and-improve-your-classificationregression-model-and-is-therefore-a-good-idea-if-true-provide-some-supporting-details-if-false-give-a-counterexample">Is the following statement true or false? “Performing k-means and then adding labels of the resulting clusters to your set of features can enhance your feature set and improve your classification/regression model and is therefore a good idea.” If true, provide some supporting details. If false, give a counterexample.</h2> <ul> <li>False. The label generated by k-means clustering and the actual label may not match. Then the clustered label may act as noise because it is not useful information. In addition, the feature space may be unnecessarily expanded. Small data and large number of clusters can lead to overfitting.</li> </ul> <h3 id="citation-9">Citation</h3> <ul> <li>Trevor Hastie, Robert Tibshirani, and Jerome Friedman (2009), Ch 14: Unsupervised Learning, The Elements of Statistical Learning: Data Mining, Inference, and Prediction (Second Edition)</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI/ML"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Answering the questions to prepare the final]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Security - Attacks</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-attacks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Security - Attacks"/><published>2024-09-22T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-22T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-attacks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-attacks/"><![CDATA[<p>There are two different types of attacks, passive attack and active attack.</p> <h1 id="passive-attack">Passive Attack</h1> <blockquote> <p>Attempt to learn or make use of information, but not affect system resources.</p> </blockquote> <p>Such as, release message contents and traffic analysis.<br/> It is relatively hard to detect, but easier to prevent by encryption.</p> <h2 id="realease-message-contents">Realease Message Contents</h2> <p>Message content is one of the passive attack. It involves the intruder stealing all the message or data transmitted. The information gathered by the intruder is stolen unethically.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Security/release_message-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Security/release_message-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Security/release_message-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Security/release_message.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="traffic-analysis">Traffic Analysis</h2> <p>Masked traffic analysis is also one of the passive attack. It involves messages or data eing encrypted before transmission. The message being masked the intruder can’t read the message but only understand the pattern and length of encryption.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Security/traffic_analysis-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Security/traffic_analysis-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Security/traffic_analysis-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Security/traffic_analysis.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h1 id="active-attack">Active Attack</h1> <blockquote> <p>Attempt to alter system resources or affect their operation.</p> </blockquote> <p>It is relatively hard to prevent because it would require physical protection of all communications facilities and paths at all times, but easier to detect.</p> <p>There are four categories.</p> <ul> <li>Maquerade</li> <li>Replay</li> <li>Modification of messages</li> <li>Denial of service</li> </ul> <h2 id="masquerade-attack">Masquerade Attack</h2> <p>The attacker tampers the information received by the receiver by claiming itself as the sender. It takes place when one entity pretends to be a different entity. It includes one of the other forms of active attack.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Security/masquerade_attack-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Security/masquerade_attack-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Security/masquerade_attack-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Security/masquerade_attack.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="replay-attack">Replay Attack</h2> <p>The attacker attacks the transmitted message through a passive channel and make the final message received by the receiver may appear to be authorized and safe. It involves the passive capture of a previously transmitted message and replaying it to produce an unauthorized effect.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Security/replay-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Security/replay-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Security/replay-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Security/replay.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="modification-attack">Modification Attack</h2> <p>Some portion of a legitimate message is altered, or messages are delayed or reordered to produce an unauthorized effect.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Security/modification-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Security/modification-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Security/modification-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Security/modification.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="denial-of-service-attack">Denial of Service Attack</h2> <p>The receiver is prevented from receiving the transmitted message as there is an overflow of requests to the receiver, which makes the services hampered from their usual behavior.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Security/server-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Security/server-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Security/server-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Security/server.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info_Security"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Information Security]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Security Policy</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Security_Policy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Security Policy"/><published>2024-09-20T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-20T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Security_Policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Security_Policy/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>A set of rules and practices that specify how a system or organization provides security services to protect its assets.</p> </blockquote> <p>Security policy defines the measures that are in place to <u>ensure the confidentiality, integrity, and availability</u> of data, networks, and system.</p> <h1 id="things-covered">Things covered</h1> <ul> <li><strong>Who can access what</strong>: explain who is allowed to use certain computers, programs, and information</li> <li><strong>How to keep data safe</strong>: provide steps for keeping data safe from being stolen or lost</li> <li><strong>What to do if something goes wrong</strong>: give instructions on how to handle problems like computer hacks, data breaches, or other security issues</li> <li><strong>Using the internet and emails safely</strong>: provide guidelines for using the internet and emails in a way that doesn’t put the organization at risk</li> <li><strong>Making sure software is up to date</strong>: explain why it’s important to regularly update software and how to do it</li> <li><strong>Training employees</strong>: include instructions for teaching employees about security risks and how to protect the organization</li> <li><strong>Physical security</strong>: might cover things like locking doors, keeping servers in safe places, and making sure only authorized people can enter certain areas</li> </ul> <h1 id="aspects-of-security">Aspects of Security</h1> <blockquote> <p>The security architecture provides a systematic approach to address the dynamic and evolving nature of security challenges in information systems.</p> </blockquote> <p>It offers a framework for organizations to build and maintain a secure environment for their <u>data, systems, and networks</u> by focusing on attacks, mechanisms, and services.</p> <h2 id="security-attack">Security Attack</h2> <p>These attacks can take <strong>various forms</strong>, unauthorized access, disclosure, modification, or destruction of data, systems, or networks.<br/> The goal is to protect against such actions and maintain the confidentiality, integrity, and availability of information (CIA Traids).</p> <h2 id="security-mechanism">Security Mechanism</h2> <p>Methods designed to detect, prevent, or recover from security attacks. They act as security barriers to safeguard an organization’s assets. They operate independently or in conjunction.</p> <h3 id="common-security-mechanisms">Common security mechanisms</h3> <ul> <li>Cryptography</li> <li>Message digests and digital signatures</li> <li>Digital certificates</li> <li>Public Key Infrastructure (PKI): A framework that manages digital keys and certificates, facilitating secure communication. &amp;nbsp Different entieties excange information using digital certification</li> </ul> <h2 id="security-service">Security Service</h2> <p>It is functionalities offered by security mechanisms to enhance the security of a system. And it represent the specific functionalities offered by security mechanisms. It can include authentication, access control, data confidentiality, data integrity, and non-repudiation.</p> <h3 id="authentication">Authentication</h3> <blockquote> <p>Used to assure the identity of the sender or creator of the data. It is a process of verifying the identity of a user, device, or system, to ensure that it is not and imposter or malicious actor.</p> </blockquote> <p>=&gt; Assure that the communicating entity is the one that it claims to be</p> <h4 id="two-specific-authentication-services">Two specific authentication services</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Peer Entity Authentication</strong>: Used to authenticate the identity of other entities with which the system is communicating</li> <li><strong>Data Origin Authentication</strong>: Used to authenticate the origin of a message or data, to ensure that it was sent by the entity that it claims to be form</li> </ul> <p>Both of these services are important for ensuring the authenticity and integrity of communication, in order to prevent unauthorized access, tampering, or impersonation. It ensures that the data or communication is from the intended source and not an imposter or an attacker.</p> <p><strong>Process</strong>: Identification -&gt; Authentication -&gt; Authorization -&gt; Auditing -&gt; Accountability -&gt; IAAA</p> <h3 id="access-control">Access Control</h3> <blockquote> <p>It used to prevent misuse of resources and ensure that only authorized users have access to the available rewources.</p> </blockquote> <p>=&gt; Prevent unauthorized use of a resource</p> <h4 id="examples">Examples</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Discretionary Access Control (DAC)</strong>: allows the owner or administrator of a resource to decide who is allowed to access it</li> <li><strong>Role-based Access Control (RBAC)</strong>: allows access based on the role of the user within the organization. ex) AWS account</li> <li><strong>Mandatory Access Control (MAC)</strong>: the access is granted based on a set of predefined rules</li> <li><strong>Attribute-based Access Control (ABAC)</strong>: the access is granted based on the attributes of the requestor, the resource, and the context in which the access request is made</li> </ul> <h3 id="data-confidentiality">Data Confidentiality</h3> <blockquote> <p>Responsible for ensuring that the data is <u>kept extremely safe from third-party intruders.</u></p> </blockquote> <p>=&gt; Protect data from unauthorized disclosure</p> <h4 id="types-of-data-confidentiality">Types of data confidentiality</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Protecting data in transit</strong>: to protect data that is being transmitted between two parties, over a network or through the internet. Can include both passive and active protection measures, encryption.</li> <li><strong>Protecting data at rest</strong>: to protect data that is <u>stored on a device or system</u>, on a HD or in a DB. Can include access controls, encryption, and backups to prevent unauthorized access or data loss.</li> <li> <p><strong>Protecting traffic flow from analysis</strong>: to protect the characteristics of the traffic flow, the source and destination, frequency, length and other characteristics of the traffic on a communication facility. Can include measures such as traffic padding and traffic encryption.</p> </li> <li>Data Confidentiality services are important for maintaining the privacy and security of sensitive information, and they can take many forms to protect data in transit, at rest and traffic flow from analysis.</li> </ul> <h3 id="data-integrity">Data Integrity</h3> <blockquote> <p>Ensure that the transmitted information received by the receiver is <strong>well-authenticated</strong> and there is <u>no tampering with the information received.</u></p> </blockquote> <p>=&gt; Assure data received are exactly as sent by authorized entity</p> <p>Helps to ensure that the data received is the same as the data that was sent and that it has not been <strong>modified</strong>, <strong>deleted</strong>, or <strong>tampered</strong> <u>with in any way.</u></p> <ul> <li>Data Integrity services are important for <u>maintaning the authenticity and accuracy of transmitted information</u>, and they can take many forms to protect a stream of messages, individual messages, or selected fields within a message.</li> </ul> <h3 id="nonrepudiation">Nonrepudiation</h3> <p>Used to prevent either sender or receiver of a transmitted message from denying that the message was sent or received.</p> <p>=&gt; Protect against denial of one entity involved in communications of having participated in communications</p> <ul> <li><strong>Message is sent</strong>: the receiver can prove that the alleged sender in fact sent the message</li> <li><strong>Message is received</strong>: the sender can prove that the alleged receiver in fact received the message</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Security/Security_Services-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Security/Security_Services-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Security/Security_Services-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Security/Security_Services.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <ul> <li><em>CS458-Introduction to Information Security</em>. (2024). Sajad Meisami, Ph.D. Illinois Institute of Technology.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info_Security"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Information Security]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Security Basic - Easiest penetration &amp;amp; Defense of Computer Systems</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-EasiestPenetration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Security Basic - Easiest penetration &amp;amp; Defense of Computer Systems"/><published>2024-09-19T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-19T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-EasiestPenetration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-EasiestPenetration/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="principle-of-easiest-penetration">Principle of Easiest Penetration</h1> <ul> <li>Security principle:<br/> &amp;nbsp - A system is only as secure as its weakest link<br/> &amp;nbsp - An attacker will often target the easiest poin of encry in a system rather than the most obvious one</li> </ul> <p>Emphasizes the importance of identifying and addressing potential vulnerabilities in a system. As well as testing and regularly reviewing the security controls that are in place.</p> <h2 id="devsecops-processing">DevSecOps processing</h2> <ol> <li>Initialization Requirement</li> <li>Design<br/> &amp;nbsp - Threat modeling: Secure Design, Archetiecture</li> <li>Build Implementation<br/> &amp;nbsp - Secure code practice</li> <li>Testing<br/> &amp;nbsp - Static Analysis, Dynamic Analysis, Interactive Analysis, SCA</li> <li>Deployment Release</li> <li>Maintenance</li> </ol> <p>Authentication \(\in\) Threat modeling</p> <h1 id="principle-of-adequate-protection">Principle of Adequate Protection</h1> <p>It highlights the need for balancing the cost of security measures with the potential impact of security incidents.<br/> Also, advises organizations not to overspend on security measures to protect a system that would only cause limited damage if compromise. This principle considers both technical and economic factors in implementing the most effective security measures to protect the assets.</p> <ul> <li>A proper security risk assessment</li> <li>To weigh the costs and the risks</li> <li>Make sure the right protection measures are in place, balance; Not too much or too little</li> </ul> <h1 id="balancing-information-security-and-access">Balancing information security and access</h1> <p>This requires a balance between ==protection and availability==, known as the security vs. accessibility trade-off.<br/> Includes balancing the need to protect sensitive information with the need to allow employees, customers, and other stakeholders access to that information.</p> <ul> <li>The goal is to find a balance that ensures the ==confidentiality, integrity, and availability of information== while enabling the organization to function effectively.</li> </ul> <h1 id="cryptography">Cryptography</h1> <blockquote> <p>Cyprtography is the practice of protecting data by convering it into an unreadable format (encryption) that can only be accessed by someone who has the proper decryption key.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="common-uses">Common uses</h2> <ul> <li>Protecting data by making it unreadable through the use of encryption algorithms</li> <li>Authenticating users with digital signatures<br/> &amp;nbsp - use a combination of encryption and hashing to prove the identity of the sender</li> <li>Authenticating transactions with cryptographic protocols, SSL/TLS<br/> &amp;nbsp - provide secure communication between web browsers and servers</li> <li>Ensuring the integrity of stored data by using cryptographic techniques<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) Message Authentication Codes (MAC)</li> <li>Aid customers’ privacy by having their personal information automatically become unreadable after a certain length of time</li> </ul> <h1 id="software-controls">Software controls</h1> <blockquote> <p>Security measure that are used to protect computer systems and networks from unauthorized access and other types of threats.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="examples">Examples</h2> <ul> <li>Passwords and other forms of access control<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) biometric authentication</li> <li>Operating systems that include built-in security features<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) user accounts and permissions, be used to separate users’ actions from each other on a system</li> <li>Virus scanners watch for some kinds of malware</li> <li>Develpment controls enforce quality measures on the original source code</li> <li>Personal firewalls</li> </ul> <h1 id="hardware-controls">Hardware controls</h1> <blockquote> <p>Security measure that use separate hardware devices to protect computer systems and networks</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="examples-1">Examples</h2> <ul> <li>Biometric readers<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) fingerprint readers</li> <li>Smart tokens<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) small and portable decices that generate one-time passcodes</li> <li>Firewalls</li> <li>Intrusion detection systems</li> </ul> <h1 id="physical-controls">Physical controls</h1> <blockquote> <p>Security measure that are designed to protect the hardware itself and prvent physical access to the console, storage media, and other critical components of a computer system or network.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="examples-2">Examples</h2> <ul> <li>Locks</li> <li>Security guards</li> <li>Off-site backups: To protect against the possibility of fire, flood, or other types of natural disasters</li> <li>Location-based controls<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) Do not put data center on a fault line in California</li> </ul> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <ul> <li><em>CS458-Introduction to Information Security</em>. (2024). Sajad Meisami, Ph.D. Illinois Institute of Technology.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info_Security"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Information Security]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Security Basic 2</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Security Basic 2"/><published>2024-09-17T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-17T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic2/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="computer-security-concepts">Computer Security Concepts</h1> <ul> <li>Asset</li> <li>Vulnerability</li> <li>Threat</li> <li>Attack</li> <li>Countermeasure or control</li> </ul> <h2 id="asset">Asset</h2> <blockquote> <p>Things might want to protect</p> </blockquote> <ol> <li>Hardware: Includeing computer systems and other data processing, data storage.</li> <li>Software: Including the operating system, system utilities, and applications.</li> <li>Data: Including files and databases, as well as security-related data.<br/> &amp;nbsp&amp;nbsp ex) password files</li> <li>Communication facilities and networks: Local and wide area network communication links, bridges, routers, and so on.</li> </ol> <h2 id="vulnerabilities">Vulnerabilities</h2> <blockquote> <p>Weaknesses or gaps in the security system that could be exploited to cause loss or harm.</p> </blockquote> <p>Weakness can be occur through flaws`, features or user error, and attackers will look to exploit any of them, often combining one or more, to achieve their end goal.</p> <p><strong>Flaws</strong></p> <ul> <li>It is an unitended funcitonality. This may either be a result of poor design or through mistakes made during implementation. Flaws may go undetected for a significant period of time. The majority of common attacks we see today exploit these types of vulnerabilities.</li> <li>Vulnerabilities are actively pursued and exploited by the full range of attackers consequently, a market has grown in software flaws, with “zero-day” vulnerabilities fetching hundreds of thousands of dollars.</li> </ul> <h3 id="examples">Examples</h3> <ul> <li>A file server that doesn’t authenticate its users</li> <li>Bad passwords</li> <li>Buggy software</li> <li>Untrained employees</li> <li>Lack of encryption</li> </ul> <h3 id="categories">Categories</h3> <ul> <li>Corrupted (Loss of integrity): The system can be <strong>corrupted</strong>, so it does the wrong thing or gives wrong answers.<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) Stored data values may differ from what they should be because they have been improperly modified.</li> <li>Leaky (Loss of confidentiality): The system can be <strong>leaky</strong>.<br/> &amp;nbsp ex) Someone who should not have access to some or all of the information available through the network obtains such access.</li> <li>Unavailable or very slow (Loss of availability): The system can become <strong>unavailable</strong> or very slow.<br/> &amp;nbsp -&gt; using the system or network becomes impossible or impractical.</li> </ul> <h2 id="threats">Threats</h2> <blockquote> <p>Threats are <strong>potentials</strong> for vulnerabilities to turn into attacks on systems. Threats are potential dangers or harmful events that could exploit vulnerabilities in a system or organization, leading to negative impacts.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="attacks">Attacks</h2> <blockquote> <p>An action which explits a vulnerability to execute a threat.</p> </blockquote> <p>Attacks (threats carried out) lead to compromises or security breaches.</p> <p>Can be classified as Passive and Active.<br/> *Passive: Attempt to learn or make use of information from the system that does not affect system resources.<br/> *Active: Attempt to alter system resources or affect their operation.</p> <p>Also be classified based on the source/origin of the attacks, Inside attack and Outside attack.<br/> *Inside attack: Initiated by entity <strong>with authorized access</strong> to system.<br/> *Outside attack: Initiated by <strong>unauthorized user</strong> of the system.</p> <h3 id="example">Example</h3> <ul> <li>Telling the file server you are a different user in an attempt to read or modifiy their files are ways to exploiting a vulnerability to damage assets.</li> <li>Bad passwords: using password crackers</li> <li>Buggy software: launching an SQL injection attack</li> <li>Untrained employees: tricking them to share their credentials</li> <li>Lack of encryption: eavesdropping on communications</li> </ul> <h2 id="risk">Risk</h2> <blockquote> <p>The potential for loss, damage or destruction of an asset as a result of a threat exploiting a vulnerability.</p> </blockquote> <p>It is the likelihood that a threat will exploit a vulnerability to cause damage to an asset.<br/> Combination of the potential impact and the probability of a threat occurring.</p> <h3 id="example-1">Example</h3> <ul> <li>Financial losses</li> <li>Loss of privacy</li> <li>Damage to your reputation</li> <li>Legal implications</li> <li>Even loss of life</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Security/Security_concepts-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Security/Security_concepts-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Security/Security_concepts-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Security/Security_concepts.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <ul> <li><em>CS458-Introduction to Information Security</em>. (2024). Sajad Meisami, Ph.D. Illinois Institute of Technology.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info_Security"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Information Security]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Security Basic 1</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Security Basic 1"/><published>2024-09-15T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-15T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Security-Basic/"><![CDATA[<p>There are few keywords in the security.</p> <ul> <li> <p><em>Confidentiality</em>:<br/> Information and data need to be kept <strong>confidential</strong> in order to protect sensitive information, personal information, trade secrets, and financial data.</p> </li> <li> <p><em>Integrity</em>:<br/> It helps to ensure the integrity of data and systems <u>by protecting against unauthorized modification or destruction</u>. It is important that maintaining the accuracy and reliability of information and systems.</p> </li> <li> <p><em>Availability</em>:</p> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info_Security"/><category term="WIL"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of Information Security]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ML PaaS Project</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/ML_Project/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ML PaaS Project"/><published>2024-05-15T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-15T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/ML_Project</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/ML_Project/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="why-start-this-project">Why start this project</h1> <p>Want to make the platform for machine learning. Also, want to make non-developer does not need to code to build machine learning.</p> <h1 id="what-is-the-goal">What is the goal</h1> <p>User does not need to make a machine learning program.</p> <h1 id="focus">Focus</h1> <p>For now, this project is focused on the clustering and classification.<br/> The other fuctions will be added.</p> <h1 id="skills">Skills</h1> <p>Use Python, AWS, and Flask</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Project"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduce ML PaaS Project]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IaaS vs PaaS vs SaaS</title><link href="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Cloud_computing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IaaS vs PaaS vs SaaS"/><published>2024-05-08T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-08T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Cloud_computing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://namdarine.github.io/blog/2024/Cloud_computing/"><![CDATA[<p>IaaS, PaaS, and SaaS are the three most popular types of cloud service offerings. They are sometimes referred to as cloud service models or cloud computing service models.</p> <h1 id="infrastructure-as-a-service">Infrastructure as a service</h1> <p>Also known as IaaS. It is on-demand access to cloud-hosted physical and virtual servers, storage, and networking - the backend IT infrastructure for running applications and workloads in the cloud. The difference is that the cloud service provider hosts, manages, and maintains the hardware and computing resources in its own data centers. IaaS customers use the hardware via an internet connection and pay for that use on a subscription or pay-as-you-go basis. Customers can provision, configure and operate the servers and infrastructure resources via a graphical dashboard, or programmatically through APIs.</p> <p>IaaS is like a Lego factory.</p> <h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2> <ol> <li><strong>Flexibility</strong> : Compared to traditional IT, IaaS gives customers more <strong>flexibility</strong> to build out computing resources as needed and to scale them up or down in response to spikes or slow-downs in traffic.</li> <li><strong>Reduction of customer costs and overhead</strong> : It lets customers avoid the up-front expense and overhead of purchasing and maintaining its own on-premises data center.</li> <li><strong>Scalability</strong> : It eliminates the constant tradeoff between the waste of purchasing excess on-premises capacity to accommodate spikes, versus the poor performance or outages that can result from not having enough capacity for unanticipated traffic bursts or growth.</li> <li><strong>Higher availability</strong> : The company can effortlessly set up backup servers and even deploy them in different locations to guarantee continued operation in case of local power failures or physical disasters.</li> <li><strong>Lower latency, and improved performance</strong> : Because IaaS providers typically operate data centers in multiple geographies, IaaS customers can locate apps and services closer to users to minimize latency and maximize performance.</li> <li><strong>Improved responsiveness</strong> : Customers can quickly set up resources, try out new ideas rapidly, and easily introduce them to a larger audience.</li> <li><strong>Comprehensive security</strong> : With strong security measures in place at the office, data centers, and encryption, organizations can often benefit from enhanced security and protection similar to what they would have if they managed the cloud infrastructure themselves.</li> <li><strong>Faster access to best-of-breed technology</strong> : Cloud providers compete by offering cutting-edge technologies to their users. Customers using IaaS can benefit from these technologies much sooner and at a lower cost compared to implementing them in their own physical locations.</li> </ol> <h2 id="usage">Usage</h2> <ul> <li>Disaster recovery</li> <li>Ecommerce</li> <li>IoT, event processing, AI</li> <li>Startups</li> <li>Software development</li> </ul> <h1 id="platform-as-a-service">Platform as a service</h1> <p>As known as PaaS. It provides a cloud-based platform for developing, running, and managing applications. The cloud services provider hosts manages and maintains all the hardware and software included in the platform, servers, OS software, storage, networking, databases, middleware, runtimes, frameworks, and development tools. Also provide related services for security, OS and software upgrades, and backups.</p> <p>Users can access PaaS through GUI. Development or DevOps teams can collaborate on all their work across the entire application lifecycle, coding, integration, testing, delivery, deployment, and feedback.</p> <p>PaaS is like a Lego brick. PaaS developer provides the Lego bricks to the software developers and the software developers make their own Lego model using the bricks. They do not need to make their own Lego bricks for their service; they just choose the bricks and pay for them.</p> <h2 id="benefits-1">Benefits</h2> <ol> <li><strong>Efficiency</strong> : Allows customers to build, test, deploy run, update, and scale applications more quickly and cost-effectively than they might if they had to build out and manage their own on-premises platform.</li> <li><strong>Faster time to market</strong> : Development teams are able to spin-up development, testing, and production environments in minutes, rather than weeks or months using PaaS.</li> <li><strong>Low- to no-risk testing and adoption of new technologies</strong> : Typically, a PaaS platform has an application that includes access to a wide range of up-to-date resources above and below the stack. This enables enterprises to operate new OS without significant investment in systems, languages, and other tools. Users can test the infrastructure required to test or run their system, language, and other tools.</li> <li><strong>Simplified collaboration</strong> : As a cloud-based service, PaaS provides a shared software development environment, giving development and operations teams access to all the tools they need, from anywhere with an Internet Connection.</li> <li><strong>A more scalable approach</strong> : With PaaS, organizations can purchase extra capacity for building, testing, staging, and running applications whenever they need it.</li> <li><strong>Less to manage</strong> : PaaS offloads infrastructure management, patches, updates, and other administrative tasks to the cloud service provider.</li> </ol> <h2 id="usage-1">Usage</h2> <ul> <li>API development and management</li> <li>IoT</li> <li>Agile development and DevOps</li> <li>Cloud-native development and hybrid cloud strategy</li> </ul> <h1 id="software-as-a-service">Software as a service</h1> <p>As known as SaaS. It is cloud-hosted, ready-to-use application software. Users pay a monthly or annual fee to use a complete application from within a web browser, desktop client, or mobile app. The application and all of the infrastructure required to deliver it-servers, storage, networking, middleware, application software, data storage-are hosted and managed by the SaaS vendor. Simply, the user does not need to download the software to use.</p> <p>The vendor manages all upgrades and patches to the software. As part of the Service Level Agreements (SLAs), vendors ensure availability, performance, and security levels. Customers can add more users and data storage on demand by paying extra.</p> <p>Email, social media, and cloud file storage solutions are examples of SaaS applications. The chatGPT is SaaS product.</p> <p>SaaS is like already made the Lego model.</p> <h2 id="benefits-2">Benefits</h2> <ol> <li><strong>Convenience</strong> : SaaS offloads all infrastructure and application management to the SaaS vendor. All the user has to do is create an account, pay the fee, and start using the application. The vendor handles everything else, from maintaining the server hardware and software to managing user access and security, storing and managing data, implementing upgrades and patches, and more.</li> <li><strong>Minimal risk</strong> : There is a free trial period or low monthly fees provided by most SaaS providers. Let customers try the software to get used to it or see if it will meet their needs.</li> <li><strong>Anytime/anywhere productivity</strong> : If there is an internet connection, the customers can use SaaS products anytime and anywhere. Adding users is as simple as registering and paying for new seats - customers can purchase more data storage for a nominal charge.</li> </ol> <p>Some SaaS vendors allow the user to customize their product from provided a companion PaaS solution.</p> <h1 id="reference">Reference</h1> <p>What are iaas, paas and SAAS?. IBM. (2024, March 8). https://www.ibm.com/topics/iaas-paas-saas</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Cloud_Computing"/><category term="WIS"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Concepts and understanding of IaaS, PaaS, and SaaS]]></summary></entry></feed>